now let's move to just a final brief discussion
about performance at this point it should
be clear that input and output and the handling
of input and output with the different
devices you have in your computer has a major
impact in system performance
we have seen this now in several examples
but it places an overhead on the CPU that
has to run several type of instructions
and sense for example if that are interrupts
it requires proper scheduling of processes
we have discussed context switches and
you know that when you have an interrupt
because of some input or some output
there will be a context switch you need to
save registers log all the registers and all these
things are ways to spend CPU cycles
not really running processes but switching
between them if you want to think about a very
extreme example of
how you can achieve significantly different
performance by the way you implement something
you can think about remote login so if you
were to do something very naive that would
be to transmit each character you type in
your keyboard when you're trying to do a remote login
one by one
and wait until you get the ack from the server
you're trying to connect before typing the
following character you can basically go through
this image and see all the steps all the interrupts
context switches access to device drivers you
will do and you would realize that this would really
perform poorly
what you probably would like to do is to wait
until everything has been written the username
or the password and then send that as a single thing
to reduce the number of times you go through
all these costly operation this is a simple
example but at this point it's not really
about the example
it's about going through this image have a look yourself
and thinking oh right now this thing is what
we discussed here this thing is what
we have discussed in the other lecturer and see
that it is a pretty long and pretty complicated
series of steps that are going to be performed
just for something like an action like typing
a
character so if you want to improve performance
then you need to reduce as much as possible
the number of context switches think for
example at having different interrupt lines
or maskable and nonmaskable interrupts you need to reduce
the number of times you copy data move
data around if it's not needed
think about the copy-on-write mechanism you
need to reduce the frequency of interrupts
so for example you use a buffer and you write to
disk only when you have enough data you
don't do that for each individual block for
example because that would result in more
interrupts that need to be handled by the
hardware and the operating
system you can use hardware support like
direct memory access and then you also can
achieve a better performance by basically
balancing the use of CPU memory and so on
so that you maximize throughput and you don't
create bottlenecks in specific components
now as always here there is a tradeoff if
you try to achieve performance with algorithms
or solution that stay at the application level
so high in the hierarchy that's good for flexibility
but in terms of real performance the benefit
might be small
if you remember now I said from the beginning
it's always cooperation between operating
system and hardware if many things have support
from the hardware itself it's because at the
end of the day if you want to achieve really
good performance you need to implement your
stuff at lower levels basically going at the
hardware level
the problem with that of course is that it
takes more time to reach that level because
there are higher development costs for that
you need to increase the abstraction level
if you find out that something is wrong that
has a significant cost to be fixed
but over time you probably want to push your
algorithms to lower levels once you see that they
actually work and they are well accepted or
used a lot by many operating systems so that
once you reach the hardware level you get
the best performance you can get